Mary Roby Papers, 1927-2012 (bulk 1959-2003)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Mary Roby Papers, 1927-2012 (bulk 1959-2003)
MS 553
Roby, Mary P.
The Mary Roby Papers (1927-2012) contain biographical materials, documents detailing the history of women’s athletics at the University of Arizona, and papers outlining Mary Roby’s leadership roles within the athletics department at the University of Arizona. Additional items in the collection include numerous photographs, awards, and memorabilia. These documents and photographs detail her legacy as an athletic administrator and pioneer of women’s competitive athletics at the university from 1959-1989.
2.5 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
Mary Roby was born in Miami, Arizona in 1926. She was a member of the Chi Omega sorority as an undergraduate student at the University of Arizona where she majored in Physical Education, graduating with a Bachelor of Science in 1948. She attended Smith College where she earned a Master of Science in Physical Education in 1949. Mary Roby graduated from the University of Southern California in 1971 with a Ph.D. in Physical Education with a concentration in sports history and administration.
She began her career as a physical education teacher and athletics coach at the University of Texas in 1949. In 1959, she accepted a position as Physical Education Instructor, Director of the Women’s Recreation Association, and athletics coach at the University of Arizona. She was an athletics administrator at the University of Arizona for 30 years, retiring in 1989.
During her tenure at the University of Arizona, Mary Roby was named the first Director of Athletics for Women in 1972 and became Associate Athletic Director for men’s and women’s athletic programs in 1982. She was a full professor in the Department of Exercise and Sports Sciences and propelled women’s athletics at the University of Arizona from intramural sports to the Intermountain, Western Collegiate Athletic Association, Pacific-West and Pacific-10 Conferences. She served on many committees at the conference level, including as Chair of the National Collegiate Athletic Association Women’s Committee on Committees from 1985-1986 and Pacific-10 conference Vice President from 1987-1988. As a professor and administrator, Mary Roby published and presented at the national, regional, state and university level. She was married to Fred Roby, a professor emeritus in the Department of Exercise and Sports Sciences at the University of Arizona.
Mary Roby received numerous awards and honors in recognition of her leadership role in women’s athletics. She was inducted into the University of Arizona Mortar Board Hall of Fame in 1981, which recognizes outstanding leadership and service. After her retirement, she was inducted into the National Association of Collegiate Directors of Athletics Hall of Fame in 1995. She continued to serve on committees and was an active member of University of Arizona athletics until her death on 30 January 2012.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series
Series I: Biographical Materials, 1948-1989
Series II: University of Arizona Women’s Athletics, 1951-2010
Series III: Photographs, 1927-2003
Series IV: Scrapbooks, 1947-2012
Series V: Awards and Memorabilia, 1975-1997
Scope and Content Note
The Mary Roby Papers document her early life and education, from her undergraduate years spent as a member of the Chi Omega Sorority at the University of Arizona to her professional life as an athletics administrator at the University of Arizona. Mary Roby’s leadership roles within the athletics department at the University are well recorded through photographic evidence and documents generated throughout the course of her career until her retirement in 1989. These records and photographs detail her legacy as an athletic administrator and document the history of women’s athletics.
University of Arizona Women's Athletics and Physical Education Papers, MS 555
Access Terms
Roby, Mary (Pavlich), 1926-2012.
University of Arizona - Faculty.
University of Arizona - Sports.
College Sports – Arizona -- Tucson.
Physical Education and Training -- Administration.
Physical Education Teachers – Arizona.
Sports for Women – Arizona – Tucson .
Articles
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Material, 1949-1989
  Biographical materials include ephemera as well biographical summaries.
  - Saint Michael’s, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Smith College – Arizona State College, 1949, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Career Achievements, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: University of Arizona Women’s Athletics, 1951-2010
  The University of Arizona Women’s Athletics series contains annual reports, newsletters, newspaper clippings, historical data and a timeline of the history of women’s sports at the university.
  - University of Arizona Women’s Athletics History, 1951-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1959-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Department of Athletics and Physical Education for Men, 1960-1961, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women’s Recreation Association Newsletters, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1967, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women’s Recreation Association Annual Report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - University of Arizona Legacy - Women’s Athletics, 1975-1989, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Women’s Intercollegiate Athletics, 1979-2010 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - University of Arizona Women’s Athletics Timeline, 1988, 1997, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Student Athlete Handbook, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - University of Arizona Women’s Sports Legacy, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Photographs, 1927-2003
  The Photographic series is extensive and includes photographs taken as early as 1927 and spans eight decades
  - Photographs, 1927-1929, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, circa 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, circa 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, circa 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, circa 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, circa 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Slides and Script - University of Arizona Women's Athletics History Presentation, circa 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mary Roby’s Retirement Party, May 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1990-1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mary Roby Award Luncheon, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - NACDA Hall of Fame Induction, June 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - University of Arizona Class of 1948 Reunion, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Naming of the Mary Roby Gymnastic Training Center, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mary Photos DVD-R, circa 2000, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series III: Scrapbooks, 1947-2012
  The Scrapbooks series is comprised of five scrapbooks documenting Mary Roby’s life as an undergraduate at the University of Arizona, her professional achievements, the naming of the Mary Roby Gymnastics Training Center, as well as a scrapbook assembled posthumously of her funeral service and legacy.
  - Chi Omega Sorority Years - University of Arizona, 1947-1949 (Box 4)
  - Mary's Retirement Party, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Nice Articles, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - Mary Roby Gymnastics Training Center, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Memories of Mary, 2012 (Box 4)
- Series V: Awards and Memorabilia, 1975-1997
  The Awards and Memorabilia series contains pins, buttons, and other commemorative items from her tenure at the University of Arizona including a plaque awarded to her upon her retirement in 1989.
  - Assorted Pins, Buttons, and Badges, 1975-1992 (Box 5)
  - Assorted Ribbons and Patches, 1997, undated (Box 5)
  - Personalized Mary Roby Wildcat Towel, undated (Box 5)
  - Plaque - Office of the Mayor Certificate of Appreciation, 1989 (Box 5)